<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author>Jürgen Jakobitsch</author>
        <title>SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp - Building</title>
    </properties>
    <meta name="keyword" content="semagrow, build"/>
    <body>
        <section name="Building">
            <p>   
                This page contains information on how to build and customize
                the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Notes</li>
                    <li>System requirements</li>                    
                    <li>Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp as a war file (default)</li>
                    <li>Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp preinstalled in a tomcat</li>
                    <li>Generating the maven-site documentation</li>
                    <li>Customizing a local installation using build properties</li>                    
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>   
        <section name="Notes">
            <ul>
                <li>The following build instructions and customizations are for development only.</li>
                <li>
                    Installation of the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp on production systems should be done 
                    using the available package manager (debian/rpm).
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>     
        <section name="System requirements">
            To be able to build the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp it is necessary that the following
            components are installed.
            <ol>
                <li>git<br/>
                    git is necessary to clone all repositories. All builds have been tested with
                    git version 1.8.1.4. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    git --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>JDK<br/>
                    A JDK (Java Development Kit) is necessary to compile all java-components. All builds
                    have been tested with java version 1.6.0_39. Please note that a JRE is not sufficient.
                    To check the installed version enter the following command in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    java -version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>Maven<br/>
                    Maven is necessary to build and assemble all components. All builds have
                    been tested with Apache Maven 3.0.3. Please make sure that mvn also uses the runtime
                    from the JDK and not from JRE. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    mvn --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Build Lifecycle bindings">
            <ol>
                <li>package
                    <ol>
                        <li>validate
                            <ol>
                                <li>Read build.properties file</li>
                                <li>Read tomcat.properties file</li>
                            </ol>                        
                        </li>
                        <li>initialize
                            <ol>
                                <li>Download tomcat to target directory</li>
                                <li>copy src/script/* files to target</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>package
                            <ol>
                                <li>Create tomcat-distribution</li>                                
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                    </ol>
                </li>
                <li>package
                    <ol>
                        <li>validate
                            <ol>
                                <li>Read build.properties file</li>
                                <li>Read tomcat.properties file</li>
                            </ol>                        
                        </li>
                        <li>initialize
                            <ol>
                                <li>Download tomcat to target directory</li>
                                <li>copy src/script/* files to target</li>
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>package
                            <ol>
                                <li>Create tomcat-distribution</li>                                
                            </ol>
                        </li>
                        <li>deploy
                            <ol>
                                <li>Deploy according to distribution.mvn settings, see below</li>                                
                            </ol>
                        </li>                        
                    </ol>
                </li>                
            </ol>
        </section>        
        <section name="Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp as a war file (default)">
            To build the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp war file simply cd into ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root}
            and issue the following command
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn clean install
</source>
            <br/>
            This will result in a deployable war file in ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root}/target.
            Please note that there might be requirements for tomcat (ie. a JNDI datasource) that must be
            taken care of individually when only building the webapp.<br/>
            It is recommended to use this build only in case you have tomcat installed ready to use the
            SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp and only want to update the webapp for testing purposes.
        </section>
        <section name="Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp preinstalled in a tomcat">
            To build a fully functional tomcat with the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp preinstalled cd into
            ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root} and issue the following command
            <br/>
<source>                
    mvn clean package -Psemagrow-stack-webapp-distribution
</source>
            <br/>
            This will result in a zip file in ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root}/target containing a fully equipped
            tomcat (in version 7.0.42 as of writing). This tomcat is configured with all dependencies (lib, JNDI) that are needed to run the 
            SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp. Please note that external dependencies need to be setup individually.
            For example a the Postgres database needs to be installed and run separately.
            In order to run SemaGrow uncompress the generated zip, copy the files from the "resources" folder 
            to /etc/default/semagrow and run the .startup.sh script located in the "bin" folder. 
            If you do not have permissions to create directories under /etc/default then copy 
             the files from the "resources" folder to /tmp  and in the resources/repository.ttl file edit line 
            "semagrow:metadataInit "/etc/default/semagrow/metadata.ttl" ;" to semagrow:metadataInit "/tmp/metadata.ttl" ;".
            Now you can run the .startup.sh script. 
            SemaGrow webapp can be accessed at http://localhost:8080/SemaGrow/ .
        </section>
        <section name="Generating the maven-site documentation">
            SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp includes an automatically generated documentation including of
            dependency and license reports as well as javadoc and highlighted source code.
            To preview the generated documentation issue the following command in a terminal
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn site:run -P semagrow-stack-webapp-documentation
</source>
            <br/>
            This will run the documentation page on a local jetty at port 8080. The documentation
            page will be accessible via http://localhost:8080. Please note that normal site deployment
            is determined by the settings in pom.xml, see below.
        </section>        
        <section name="Customizing a local installation using build properties">
            SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp uses three property files with properties that can be overriden.
            <ul>
                <li>build.properties<br/>
                General build properties.                    
                </li>
                <li>tomcat.properties<br/>
                Properties with which the tomcat distribution is customized.
                </li>
                <li>distribution.mvn<br/>
                Property concerning the target of the deploy goal on a local machine.
                </li>
                <li>distribution.site<br/>
                Property concerning the target of the site-deploy goal on a local machine.
                </li>                
            </ul>
            <subsection name="build.properties">
                <ul>
                    <li>distribution.mvn<br/>
                    The properties file is empty as of writing but reserved for future use.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="tomcat.properties">
                <ul>
                    <li>tomcat.version<br/>
                    This property determines the version of the tomcat to be used for the distribution.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </subsection>                              
            <subsection name="Overriding property files">
                To override above property files create an own properties file (either the build or the tomcat) 
                outside of ${semagrow-stack-webapp.root} and let maven use these properties instead
                of the default ones.
                To do so a settings.xml must be created, if it doesn't already exist, in the local maven repository
                which is usually in ~/.m2 (= /home/${username}/.m2 .
                see <a href="http://maven.apache.org/settings.html" target="_blank">here</a> for an empty settings.xml template.
                In the profiles section of the settings.xml create a new profile for the semagrow-stack-webapp build environment
                and mark it as active in the activeProfiles section.
<source>
    &lt;profiles&gt;
        &lt;profile&gt;
            &lt;id&gt;semagrow-stack-webapp&lt;/id&gt;
            &lt;properties&gt;
                &lt;tomcat.properties>/path/to/custom/tomcat.properties&lt;/tomcat.properties&gt;
            &lt;/properties&gt;
        &lt;/profile&gt;
    &lt;/profiles&gt;
    &lt;activeProfiles&gt;
        &lt;activeProfile&gt;semagrow-stack-webapp&lt;/activeProfile&gt;
    &lt;/activeProfiles&gt;
</source>
            </subsection>  
            <subsection name="Overriding distribution properties">
                To change the maven distribution (site distribution) target of a local installation either add the property distribution.mvn 
                (distribution.site) to an active profile in a local settings.xml (see above) or start the build with another system parameter
                using the -D option, for example
<source>
  mvn clean deploy -Psemagrow-stack-webapp-distribution -Ddistribution.mvn=/path/to/some/maven/repo
</source>                                
            This will install the war file along with the distribution zip file to the given maven repo.
<source>
  mvn clean site-deploy -Psemagrow-stack-webapp-distribution -Ddistribution.site=/path/to/some/maven/site
</source>                                
            This will install the documentation files to the given maven directory.
            </subsection>              
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
