<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author>Jürgen Jakobitsch</author>
        <title>SemaGrow-Stack-Modules-Sails-Powder - Building</title>
    </properties>
    <meta name="keyword" content="semagrow, build"/>
    <body>
        <section name="Building">
            <p>
                This page contains information on how to build and customize
                the SemaGrow-Stack-Modules.
            </p>
            <p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Notes</li>
                    <li>System requirements</li>
                    <li>Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Modules as jar files (default)</li>
                    <li>Generating the maven-site documentation</li>
                </ol>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Notes">
            <ul>
                <li>The following build instructions and customizations are for development only.</li>
                <li>
                    Installation of the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp on production systems should be done
                    using the available package manager (debian/rpm).
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="System requirements">
            To be able to build the SemaGrow-Stack-Webapp it is necessary that the following
            components are installed.
            <ol>
                <li>git<br/>
                    git is necessary to clone all repositories. All builds have been tested with
                    git version 1.8.1.4. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    git --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>JDK<br/>
                    A JDK (Java Development Kit) is necessary to compile all java-components. All builds
                    have been tested with java version 1.6.0_39. Please note that a JRE is not sufficient.
                    To check the installed version enter the following command in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    java -version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
                <li>Maven<br/>
                    Maven is necessary to build and assemble all components. All builds have
                    been tested with Apache Maven 3.0.3. Please make sure that mvn also uses the runtime
                    from the JDK and not from JRE. To check the installed version enter the following command
                    in a terminal
                    <br/>
<source>
    mvn --version
</source>
                    <br/>
                </li>
            </ol>
        </section>
        <section name="Building the SemaGrow-Stack-Modules as jar files">
            To build all semagrow-stack-modules file simply cd into ${semagrow-stack-modules.root}
            and issue the following command
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn clean install
</source>
            <br/>
            This will result in a jar file in the target directory of the respective module and also
            deploy the jars to the local maven repository (~/.m2/repository on linux).
        </section>
        <section name="Generating the maven-site documentation">
            SemaGrow-Stack-Modules includes an automatically generated documentation including of
            dependency and license reports as well as javadoc and highlighted source code.
            To preview the generated documentation issue the following command in a terminal
            <br/>
<source>
    mvn site:run -P semagrow-stack-modules-documentation
</source>
            <br/>
            This will run the documentation page on a local jetty at port 8080. The documentation
            page will be accessible via http://localhost:8080. Please note that normal site deployment
            is determined by the settings in pom.xml, see below.
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
